A Guide to the Alice Sufit Papers, 1920-2009
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Alice Sufit Papers, 1920-2009
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 194
6 boxes.
Sufit, Alice Elizabeth, 1918-2012
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth Sufit, daughter of Alice Sufit, on April 27, 2012.
Historical Information
Alice Sufit (1918-2012) was a local activist and teacher. Active in several local civic and political affairs, Sufit played integral roles on many councils, committees, and boards for Arlington County. Additionally, she completed much of her work as a longstanding member of the local chapter of the League of Women Voters. Sufit most often fought to improve education, voting rights, and women's rights in Arlington and Virginia.
Sufit was born Alice Rotzch in McKeesport, Pennsylvania, on September 28, 1918. She attended the University of Pittsburgh and moved to Washington, D.C. in 1939. She enlisted in the WAVES (Women Accepted for Volunteer Emergency Service) in the United States Naval Reserve as a lieutenant during World War II and served from 1943-1948 and worked in the Naval Research Laboratory. During this time, she met her husband Herb Sufit. The two married in 1948 and moved to Arlington.
A few years after moving to Arlington, Sufit joined the Arlington League of Women Voters. She chaired several local and state-level study committees, lobbied politicians, and held board positions. She filled many leadership roles, including Vice President in 1958, President from 1960-1961, and Co-President from 1997-1999. She also became part of the League of Women Voters of Virginia State Board in the 1970s and worked hard to revise the "Your Virginia Government" publication. Her additional civic work included membership with the American Association of University Women, including acting as President from 1989-1992. She served on the Arlington County Planning Commission in 1962 and the Commission on the Status of Women. During her tenure on the Commission on the Status of Women, she helped conduct an exhaustive study on discrimination practices against women in Arlington in schools, government, business, and banking. This report led to the permanent establishment of the Commission on the Status of Women in the county. She was award Arlington County's "Person of Vision" award in 1998 to commemorate her outstanding civic career.
Sufit earned two graduate degrees (M.A. and M. Phil) from George Washington University in political science and education. In 1961, she began a twenty-year career as a social studies teacher in the Arlington County Public Schools, where she taught at Wakefield High School. After retirement, Sufit served on the school system's social studies advisory committee and the six-year planning committee.
Sufit passed away on August 23, 2012.
Scope and Content
This collection spans just over two linear feet. Though materials date from 1920-2009, only one item dates from 1920. All other materials span from the 1950s to 2009, with the bulk of materials from the 1990s and 2000s. The materials largely constitute the records Sufit accrued during her career with the League of Women Voters, especially during the 1980s-2000s. Most of these materials are from research she conducted into various issues the League tackled (i.e. campaign reform, redistricting, etc.), though there are also bulletins, speeches Sufit gave, and other League of Women Voters operational materials. The collection contains some documents and publications Sufit acquired serving on county boards and commissions, such as the Planning Commission and the Commission on the Status of Women. There are a few materials from classes Sufit taught and took and some publications from Rock Spring Congregational Church.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into six series based on subject manner. When possible, original file names have been preserved in quotes (" ") and additions to titles from the archivist have been included in brackets ([ ]) where clarification was needed.
Series 1 contains the materials Sufit accrued as part of the League of Women Voters. Most appear to be from her involvement with the local Arlington branch, but there are other materials from the Virginia state chapter. This series is divided into several subseries, including Bulletins and Newsletters; League of Women Voters of Arlington Operations; Personal Materials (developed around a file Sufit labeled as "Personal Materials"); and Studies and Initiatives.
Series 2 houses the materials Sufit acquired from Arlington County. Most of these are related to city planning and research Sufit completed on the history and demographics of Arlington. Series 3 contains Sufit's materials related to teaching and education, including a few classes she took and her papers from the Social Studies Advisory Committee. Series 4 holds her papers related to various women's rights and women's history initiatives. Series 5 contains assorted papers and research materials related to politics. Finally, Series 6 has various publications from the Rock Spring Congregational Church.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Researchers should consult RG 44, League of Women Voters of Arlington, due to Sufit's long involvement with the League of Women Voters in Arlington. Other collections related to Sufit's career and civic activism may be of use as well, including RG 7, Arlington County Public Schools, RG 33, American Association of University Women of Arlington, and RG 35, Commission on the Status of Women, Arlington County.
Index Terms
Subjects:
League of Women Voters of Arlington; Women -- United States -- Societies and clubs.; Women in community organization; Arlington County (Va.) -- Politics and government.; Voting -- United States.; Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- League of Women Voters
  - Bulletins and Newsletters
    - League of Women Voters of Arlington Bulletin, May 1978 (Box 1)
    - "LWV Arlington Bulletin," 1999-2001 (Box 1)
    - "Arlington LWV 2000-01, 2002-2003" Bulletins, Initiatives, and Supplemental Materials, 1998, 2000-2003 (Box 1)
    - League of Women Voters of Arlington Bulletins, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
    - "Arlington-LWV 2003-2004" Bulletins and related clippings, 2003-2004 (Box 1)
    - "LWV-Arlington 2005-2006 Bulletins," 2004-2006 (Box 1)
    - "LWV-Arlington 2006-2007" Bulletins, 2006-2007 (Box 1)
    - League of Women Voters of Arlington Bulletins, 2007-2008 (Box 1)
    - The Virginia Voter Newsletter, 1968, 1986, 2002 (Box 1)
    - LWV National Voter Bulletin and Clippings on Political Issues, 1992, 2004-2009 (Box 1)
    - Assorted League of Women Voters Pamphlets, 1920, 1985, 1997, 2006, n.d. (Box 1)
  - League of Women Voters of Arlington Operations
    - League of Women Voters of Arlington Membership and President Lists, 1944-1989," 1989 (Box 2)
    - League of Women Voters of Arlington Annual Meetings, 2004, 2006, 2008 (Box 2)
    - "League of Women Voters Scholarship Committee, 2001 + 2002," 2000-2002 (Box 2)
    - "Arlington League of Women Voters Stationery," n.d. (Box 2)
    - Clippings, Arlington League of Women Voters, 1 1996, 2001 (Box 2)
    - League of Women Voters of Arlington 40th Anniversary Photograph, 1984 (Box 2)
    - "Virginia League of Women Voters 99-2000-01" Handbook, History, Delegate Workbook, Election Reform Articles, 1995, 1999-2001 (Box 2)
  - Personal Materials
    - "Personal League Stuff," including bulletins, speeches, correspondence, research, and convention materials, 1963, 1977, 1997-1999 (Box 2)
    - "Alice Sufit Speech 8/26/97 to Federal Employees at Dulles Airport," on 150th Anniversary of First Women's Rights Convention, 1997 (Box 2)
    - League of Women Voters Honorable Life Member and Past President Ribbon, n.d. (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Correspondence, 1997, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Studies and Initiatives
    - League of Women Voters of Virginia Study Guidelines, 1990, 1991, 1995 (Box 2)
    - "League of Women Voters Citizen Advisory Group Study," 1995-1997 (Box 2)
    - "League of Women Voters of Virginia Materials for Local [Delegation of] Powers State Study, December 1990," 1987-1991 (Box 2)
    - League of Women Voters Redistricting Documents and League of Women Voters Statistics, 1985, 1996, 2001, 2004-2006 (Box 2)
    - "Redistricting-League of Women Voters of Virginia 2005," 1982, 1984, 2001, 2004-2006 (Box 2)
    - "League of Women Voters of Virginia Campaign Reform and June '93 Statement," 1985, 1988-1994, 1997, 1998 (Box 2)
    - League of Women Voters of Virginia Materials on Virginia Taxes, 1976-1978 (Box 2)
    - League of Women Voters of Arlington, Study of Programs, Services, and Facilities of Arlington County Department of Parks, Recreation, and Community Resources, 1999-2000 (Box 2)
    - Histories of Virginia, Northern Virginia, and Virginia League of Women Voters by the Arlington League of Women Voters, 1953, 1960, 1982, 1983 (Box 3)
    - "League of Women Voters of Virginia History," 1969, 1977, 1982-1984, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Women's Rights and Equal Rights Amendment, 1987, 1991 (Box 3)
    - "Ms. Jean McCart, League of Women Voters, Virginia Women's Cultural History Project," 1983-1985 (Box 3)
    - "Arlington League of Women Voters Articles of Interest, Historical, etc" Initiatives on League of Women Voters Bilingual Education Position and Housing Position, 1996, 1999 (Box 3)
    - "League of Women Voters-Adult Education in Arlington County-Effective Citizenship," 1972, 1977, 1996 (Box 3)
    - League of Women Voters of Virginia Education Study, 2003 (Box 3)
- Local Government, Planning, and Arlington History
  - Arlington County Demographics and Local Governance, 1960, 1967, 1975, 1980, 1983, 1984, 1986-1990, 1994, 1995, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Arlington County [history and governance] prior to 2000," 1965, 1966, 1975, 1976, 1979, 1987, 1989, 2001, 2002, 2007 (Box 3)
  - "Arlington County Government, Census, Budgets, etc. 1990s," 1984, 1986, 1988, 1990-1992, 1994, 1996 (Box 3)
  - "Arlington County from 2000" History, Local Government, and Demographics, 2001-2007 (Box 3)
  - Arlington County City Planning and Neighborhood Conservation Booklets, 1960, 1961, 1966, 1986, 2000, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous General City Planning Pamphlets and Booklets, 1965, 1969, 1973, 1974, 1977 (Box 4)
- Teaching and Education
  - Washington Center for Metropolitan Studies and the American University Coursework on Cities, 1961, 1962, 1972 (Box 4)
  - US Government Teaching Materials, HB Woodlawn, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - Local History Teaching, Arlington Public Schools, 1983, 1989 (Box 4)
  - Social Studies Curriculum Advisory Committee, Arlington County Public Schools, 1981, 1989, 1991 (Box 4)
  - WETA Voting Guide for Teachers, 1992 (Box 4)
- Women's Initiatives
  - Arlington County Commission on the Status of Women, 1999-2000 (Box 4)
  - Arlington Women: Facts, Frustrations, and Future Book, Supplemental Materials, and Speech, 1974, 1998 (Box 5)
  - Women's Rights Papers, Diane P. Wood, Circuit Judge, US Court of Appeals for 7th Circuit, 2006 (Box 5)
  - Women in Virginia Legislature, 1998 (Box 5)
- Politics
  - "Electoral Reform Systems," 1976, 1980, 1999-2000 (Box 5)
  - Voter Registration Folder and Documents, 1998-1999 (Box 5)
  - "BPW Lobby Workshop" Lobbying Guidelines, 1996, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Money in Politics and Campaign Finance Reform Research Materials, 1992, 1995, 1996 (Box 5)
  - History and Information on Virginia Legislature, 1968-1970, 1972, 1973, 1976, 1979, 1981, 1984, 1988 (Box 5)
  - "Florida Voting and Count," 2000 Presidential Election Clippings, 2000-2001 (Box 5)
  - Political Reform Booklets-Electoral College, Civil Rights, Political Process and Transparency, 1966, 1967, 1974, 1976 (Box 5)
  - "Virginia News Letter," Weldon Cooper Center for Public Service, 2000 (Box 5)
- Rock Spring Congregational Church
  - Rock Spring Congregational Church Booklets (Mature Faith, Dinosaurs at Easter and Other Sermons, Jubilee Notes and Reflections: Celebrating 75 Years, and Making History: Celebrating 75 Years), 1978, 1987, 2001 (Box 5)
- OVERSIZE BOX 1
  - Rosslyn's Centennial Newspaper, Arlington Courier, 1988
  - Washington Post, Election 2000 Issue, 2000